<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://arunbaby0.github.io/arunbaby.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://arunbaby0.github.io/arunbaby.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-09-07T00:42:46+05:30</updated><id>https://arunbaby0.github.io/arunbaby.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Arun Baby</title><subtitle>My ramblings.</subtitle><author><name>Arun Baby</name></author><entry><title type="html">Evaluated Experience</title><link href="https://arunbaby0.github.io/arunbaby.com/thoughts/person-and-perspective/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Evaluated Experience" /><published>2020-09-06T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-09-06T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>https://arunbaby0.github.io/arunbaby.com/thoughts/person-and-perspective</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://arunbaby0.github.io/arunbaby.com/thoughts/person-and-perspective/">&lt;p&gt;Is someone separate from their perspective? How can we disentangle these two?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We often have some hard feeling towards someone because of the perspective of that person, but we equate the person to the perspective. They might have expressed something, which irritated you, because of their particular perspective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A person’s perspective is not permanent. It changes for many reasons.
It would be very easy to understand people once we understand this concept. Trying to understand the person’s perspective often opens the door to strengthen the relationship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How do you separate the person from the perspective? Whenever you try to judge someone, take a pause and think why that person is thinking that way?
This is applicable for ourself as well. Think about why we are thinking what we think to open the door to a different level of understanding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;P.S. If you are interested google “metacognition” and go down the rabbit hole.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Arun Baby</name></author><category term="thoughts" /><category term="perspective" /><summary type="html">Is someone separate from their perspective? How can we disentangle these two?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Evaluated Experience</title><link href="https://arunbaby0.github.io/arunbaby.com/thoughts/evaluated-experience/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Evaluated Experience" /><published>2020-09-05T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-09-05T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>https://arunbaby0.github.io/arunbaby.com/thoughts/evaluated-experience</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://arunbaby0.github.io/arunbaby.com/thoughts/evaluated-experience/">&lt;p&gt;It is a standard consensus that experience is the best teacher. How does just the experience can be the best teacher?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A person can have the same experience multiple times and still doesn’t learn anything. Think about a person who gets into relationship after relationship and just fail every time. What could that person have done differently?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Evaluated experience is the best teacher. Yes, evaluation is painful, so is not changing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An evaluation may be painful for most of us. The length of the suffering can be reduced significantly if we are ready to evaluate and learn from the experience.  Others may cause pain, but we are causing suffering for us. Unfortunately, letting go is not that simple.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What experiences are worth evaluating? How often are we evaluating? What is the basis for the evaluation? All these are decided by us. The power is with us.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Arun Baby</name></author><category term="thoughts" /><category term="experience" /><summary type="html">It is a standard consensus that experience is the best teacher. How does just the experience can be the best teacher?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Catch up with status quo</title><link href="https://arunbaby0.github.io/arunbaby.com/thoughts/status-game/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Catch up with status quo" /><published>2020-09-04T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-09-04T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>https://arunbaby0.github.io/arunbaby.com/thoughts/status-game</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://arunbaby0.github.io/arunbaby.com/thoughts/status-game/">&lt;p&gt;What if you could get rid of the idea that you always need to catch-up with your peers status wise? What changes will you make in your life? What stops you from doing that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Will you hold on to your job/relationships/activities? Do you want that shiny new object? Is that object a necessity or just a show-off to others?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Advertising has us chasing cars and clothes, working jobs we hate so we can buy shit we don’t need. We’re the middle children of history, man. No purpose or place. We have no Great War. No Great Depression. Our Great War’s a spiritual war… our Great Depression is our lives. We’ve all been raised on television to believe that one day we’d all be millionaires, and movie gods, and rock stars. But we won’t. And we’re slowly learning that fact. And we’re very, very pissed off. — fight club&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are the things we think we want are the things that we genuinely want? Or, someone had programmed you into thinking that you want it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What if you could relive yesterday? What changed would you make? What changes are you making for tomorrow?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Arun Baby</name></author><category term="thoughts" /><category term="status" /><summary type="html">What if you could get rid of the idea that you always need to catch-up with your peers status wise? What changes will you make in your life? What stops you from doing that?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Conformist</title><link href="https://arunbaby0.github.io/arunbaby.com/thoughts/conformist/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Conformist" /><published>2020-09-03T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-09-03T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>https://arunbaby0.github.io/arunbaby.com/thoughts/conformist</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://arunbaby0.github.io/arunbaby.com/thoughts/conformist/">&lt;p&gt;If everything you believe is something that you are supposed to believe, what is the odds that it is really a coincidence?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How many of your opinions are you reluctant to express inform of your friends/colleagues? Why so?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the answer to the above question is ‘None’, step back and give it a thought. Odds are you are thinking in a way that you are told.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other way to get the same answer is that you independently thought about each and every possibility for each of these scenarios and end up having the exact same answer. This is a highly unlikely scenario for obvious reasons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Artists put voluntary mistakes so that they can identify when someone copies their work. So are mapmakers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What are we trading for being conformist? If every generation had only conformists, the science/technology/medicine wouldn’t have evolved this much. It’s the outlaws/renegades/uncoventionals that bring real change to the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Use your brain, start thinking about why you are thinking what you think? Are you just already too much programmed?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Arun Baby</name></author><category term="thoughts" /><category term="conformist" /><category term="learning" /><summary type="html">If everything you believe is something that you are supposed to believe, what is the odds that it is really a coincidence?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Learning vs Education</title><link href="https://arunbaby0.github.io/arunbaby.com/thoughts/learning-vs-education/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Learning vs Education" /><published>2020-09-02T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-09-02T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>https://arunbaby0.github.io/arunbaby.com/thoughts/learning-vs-education</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://arunbaby0.github.io/arunbaby.com/thoughts/learning-vs-education/">&lt;p&gt;Education is the industrial process of making people compliant. Command and control is the backbone of it. 
While learning is unleashing of a curious mind against the unknown. It is wandering through foreign territories. It can be guided or unguided.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The results that anyone wants to obtain through education is well defined. It can be a certificate or a degree. An external agency sets the limits for industrial education.
The learner sets the limit for the learning.  Learning must be an engaging journey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to learn how to bicycle, don’t read a book, get on one and make mistakes. The fastest way to learn anything is by actively involving in an activity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the internet age, all you want to learn is a click away. Are we making use of all the resources that we have?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The illiterate of the 21st century will not be those who cannot read and write, but those &lt;strong&gt;who cannot learn, unlearn, and relearn&lt;/strong&gt;. – Alvin Toffler&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please don’t confuse education with learning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How much are you learning? What all you want to discover? What stops you from acquiring that skill that you always wanted to master?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Arun Baby</name></author><category term="thoughts" /><category term="education" /><category term="learning" /><summary type="html">Education is the industrial process of making people compliant. Command and control is the backbone of it. While learning is unleashing of a curious mind against the unknown. It is wandering through foreign territories. It can be guided or unguided.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Pleasure vs happiness</title><link href="https://arunbaby0.github.io/arunbaby.com/thoughts/pleasure-vs-happiness/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Pleasure vs happiness" /><published>2020-09-01T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-09-01T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>https://arunbaby0.github.io/arunbaby.com/thoughts/pleasure-vs-happiness</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://arunbaby0.github.io/arunbaby.com/thoughts/pleasure-vs-happiness/">&lt;p&gt;The former is about taking, whereas the latter is all about giving. One is short-lived and the other is long-lived.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How many of us prioritise &lt;strong&gt;happiness over pleasure&lt;/strong&gt;? When does the pleasure become indulgence? That last bag of Cheetos, one more episode in the NetFlix past midnight… Are those really helping us?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please &lt;strong&gt;don’t confuse self-care with pleasure&lt;/strong&gt;. Self-care is a necessity whereas the pleasure is completely optional.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The things which build up over a long term which doesn’t give instant joy mostly is related to happiness. For example, exercise, building skills can all bring happiness in the long run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is pleasure evil? &lt;strong&gt;No&lt;/strong&gt;. It’s the &lt;strong&gt;imbalance which creates a real problem&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which one do we long for? Which one should we prioritise? How do we balance? The real battle is within.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Arun Baby</name></author><category term="thoughts" /><category term="pleasure" /><category term="happiness" /><summary type="html">The former is about taking, whereas the latter is all about giving. One is short-lived and the other is long-lived.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">First post</title><link href="https://arunbaby0.github.io/arunbaby.com/general/first-post/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="First post" /><published>2020-08-31T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-08-31T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>https://arunbaby0.github.io/arunbaby.com/general/first-post</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://arunbaby0.github.io/arunbaby.com/general/first-post/">&lt;p&gt;Hello world, and everyone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Started this blog as a means to communicate to the world. I know I am gonna make a lot of mistakes here. I am not afraid to make mistakes anymore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;task-lists&quot;&gt;Task Lists&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;task-list&quot;&gt;
  &lt;li class=&quot;task-list-item&quot;&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; class=&quot;task-list-item-checkbox&quot; disabled=&quot;disabled&quot; /&gt;Blog daily&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li class=&quot;task-list-item&quot;&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; class=&quot;task-list-item-checkbox&quot; disabled=&quot;disabled&quot; /&gt;Update the website with relevent information&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Arun Baby</name></author><category term="general" /><category term="first" /><category term="start" /><summary type="html">Hello world, and everyone.</summary></entry></feed>