<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://www.arunbaby.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://www.arunbaby.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-06-19T18:34:21+05:30</updated><id>https://www.arunbaby.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Arun Baby</title><subtitle>My ramblings.</subtitle><author><name>Arun Baby</name></author><entry><title type="html">What is the most difficult 3 words to say?</title><link href="https://www.arunbaby.com/thoughts/most-difficult-three-words/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What is the most difficult 3 words to say?" /><published>2020-09-12T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-09-12T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>https://www.arunbaby.com/thoughts/most-difficult-three-words</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.arunbaby.com/thoughts/most-difficult-three-words/">&lt;p&gt;“I don’t know”. It is the acceptance of our limited knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Does our culture encourage us to practise this? Not knowing is mostly associated with ignorance for most people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why is it difficult for us to see the limitations of our perspective? Is it difficult for a fish to see water?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There can have no argument between two people who says “I don’t know”, It will only be a discussion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Does acknowledging our limited knowledge make us any inferior person?  Once you admit to not knowing, your knowledge will have much greater value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once we accept the fact that we don’t know, the real possibility of exploration starts. Anything is possible once we follow our curiosity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do we need to know everything in the entire cosmos? Not really, I think. We hardly need to know anything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do I know the answers to the above questions at least? well, I DON’T.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Arun Baby</name></author><category term="thoughts" /><category term="difficult" /><category term="dont" /><summary type="html">“I don’t know”. It is the acceptance of our limited knowledge.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Winning a game</title><link href="https://www.arunbaby.com/thoughts/winning-a-game/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Winning a game" /><published>2020-09-11T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-09-11T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>https://www.arunbaby.com/thoughts/winning-a-game</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.arunbaby.com/thoughts/winning-a-game/">&lt;p&gt;What does it mean to win a game? Many people try to win every game. But at what cost, what was the point of winning?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are all playing one game or the other 24x7. Are we conscious of the games that we are playing?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We define the rules sometimes for the games; Some time its others. Sometimes we play the games we know we can’t win.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes we try to modify the rules of the game while we are playing, to increase the odds of our winning. what greatness is there in that kind of wins. You could have chosen the right game to play in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In some games, both parties can win. This increases the odds of having a good relationship with the other players.
In some, we have to trash others to win the game. This often ends up in toxic relationships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many games are played in the mind initially. Why are we even obsessed with winning the game, if we don’t care about the outcomes?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best strategy to win at some of the games is just by not playing it. 
Our economy thrives on selling our attention to advertisers. When a battalion of scientists fights for our attention, by all means, the best strategy to win that game is not by playing it.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Arun Baby</name></author><category term="thoughts" /><category term="winning" /><category term="game" /><summary type="html">What does it mean to win a game? Many people try to win every game. But at what cost, what was the point of winning?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Intelligence</title><link href="https://www.arunbaby.com/thoughts/intelligence/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Intelligence" /><published>2020-09-10T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-09-10T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>https://www.arunbaby.com/thoughts/intelligence</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.arunbaby.com/thoughts/intelligence/">&lt;p&gt;Are we intelligent? Will any intelligent person think themself of intelligent?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An intelligent person will be aware of the loopholes in their thinking. And someone who thinks of themselves as intelligent may be unaware of their state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The measure of intelligence is the ability to change - Albert Einstein.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This quote goes per darwin’s theory of evolution. The entire theory points out the importance of adaptability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Don’t confuse education with intelligence - unknown&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The compliance training(aka education) has nothing to do with intelligence. Also, the real learning doesn’t have to be for any labels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What if you stop trying to look intelligent and start trying to do something important? Isn’t that a better way to learn? An intelligent way?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Arun Baby</name></author><category term="thoughts" /><category term="Intelligence" /><summary type="html">Are we intelligent? Will any intelligent person think themself of intelligent?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Entitlement</title><link href="https://www.arunbaby.com/thoughts/entitlement/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Entitlement" /><published>2020-09-09T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-09-09T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>https://www.arunbaby.com/thoughts/entitlement</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.arunbaby.com/thoughts/entitlement/">&lt;p&gt;Are we entitled to have something for sure? Are we even entitled to think about our entitlement?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is there a good amount of entitlement that we need to have? Can it be an exaggerated feeling of self-importance?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A study had shown that some amount of entitlement is linked to increased creativity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we think we are entitled to something, what is the basis on which we are making that assumption? How can we validate that assumption?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Can we avoid disappointment if we just avoid the feeling of entitlement?
Are we even entitled for the necessities? The things that we take for granted, does it make to rethink about those? Especially with the pandemic where it forced us to rethink many things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is entitlement another label that we carry, which on removal give &lt;em&gt;mukthi&lt;/em&gt; for us?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Arun Baby</name></author><category term="thoughts" /><category term="entitlement" /><summary type="html">Are we entitled to have something for sure? Are we even entitled to think about our entitlement?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Non-resistance</title><link href="https://www.arunbaby.com/thoughts/non-resistance/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Non-resistance" /><published>2020-09-08T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-09-08T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>https://www.arunbaby.com/thoughts/non-resistance</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.arunbaby.com/thoughts/non-resistance/">&lt;p&gt;The dictionary meaning “the principles or practice of passive submission to constituted authority even when unjust or oppressive” doesn’t capture the eastern philosophy of non-resistance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Don’t get set into one form, adapt it and build your own, and let it grow, be like water. Empty your mind, be formless, shapeless — like water. Now you put water in a cup, it becomes the cup; You put water into a bottle it becomes the bottle; You put it in a teapot it becomes the teapot. Now water can flow or it can crash. Be water, my friend. - Bruce lee&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The eastern philosophy is about resistance to growth, whether it is physical or mental. It is freedom from the resistance that’s built by ourself. In soft martial arts, we don’t suppress the blow from the opponent using any force, we just work around it and direct it back to the person.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the focus is on the aspects of how things should have been, or the way someone treated us, when we rely on the perceived norms of society, when we cannot accept things as they are, we are being resistant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is similar to the idea of getting identified with labels. You are resisting the growth once you start identifying with labels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How can we practise non-resistance? What barriers that we have already created in our minds? Be like water, my friend.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Arun Baby</name></author><category term="thoughts" /><category term="non-resistance" /><summary type="html">The dictionary meaning “the principles or practice of passive submission to constituted authority even when unjust or oppressive” doesn’t capture the eastern philosophy of non-resistance.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Leverage</title><link href="https://www.arunbaby.com/thoughts/leverage/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Leverage" /><published>2020-09-07T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-09-07T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>https://www.arunbaby.com/thoughts/leverage</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.arunbaby.com/thoughts/leverage/">&lt;p&gt;Leverage is something you can use to get maximum advantage of something. It is a tool. For you to use a tool, first you have to understand the fundamental principles about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the age of the internet where every information ever created is accessible instantly with a few click, we have so much potential to create a greater good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just like any tool, things can be used in good and bad ways(even though the good and bad is just relative). You need to put in a lot of effort to master tools.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Give me a lever long enough and a fulcrum on which to place it, and I shall move the world.- Archimedes&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is the best tool to master? Mind? It is also the hardest to master. How much time and effort are you putting to master your mind? The first and greatest battle is always within.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How conscious are we in choosing our tools? How much mastery do you have over it? How are you planning to master new tools?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Arun Baby</name></author><category term="thoughts" /><category term="leverage" /><summary type="html">Leverage is something you can use to get maximum advantage of something. It is a tool. For you to use a tool, first you have to understand the fundamental principles about it.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Person and perspective</title><link href="https://www.arunbaby.com/thoughts/person-and-perspective/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Person and perspective" /><published>2020-09-06T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-09-06T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>https://www.arunbaby.com/thoughts/person-and-perspective</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.arunbaby.com/thoughts/person-and-perspective/">&lt;p&gt;Is someone separate from their perspective? How can we disentangle these two?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We often have some hard feeling towards someone because of the perspective of that person, but we equate the person to the perspective. They might have expressed something, which irritated you, because of their particular perspective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A person’s perspective is not permanent. It changes for many reasons.
It would be very easy to understand people once we understand this concept. Trying to understand the person’s perspective often opens the door to strengthen the relationship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How do you separate the person from the perspective? Whenever you try to judge someone, take a pause and think why that person is thinking that way?
This is applicable for ourself as well. Think about why we are thinking what we think to open the door to a different level of understanding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;P.S. If you are interested google “metacognition” and go down the rabbit hole.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Arun Baby</name></author><category term="thoughts" /><category term="perspective" /><summary type="html">Is someone separate from their perspective? How can we disentangle these two?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Evaluated Experience</title><link href="https://www.arunbaby.com/thoughts/evaluated-experience/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Evaluated Experience" /><published>2020-09-05T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-09-05T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>https://www.arunbaby.com/thoughts/evaluated-experience</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.arunbaby.com/thoughts/evaluated-experience/">&lt;p&gt;It is a standard consensus that experience is the best teacher. How does just the experience can be the best teacher?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A person can have the same experience multiple times and still doesn’t learn anything. Think about a person who gets into relationship after relationship and just fail every time. What could that person have done differently?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Evaluated experience is the best teacher. Yes, evaluation is painful, so is not changing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An evaluation may be painful for most of us. The length of the suffering can be reduced significantly if we are ready to evaluate and learn from the experience.  Others may cause pain, but we are causing suffering for us. Unfortunately, letting go is not that simple.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What experiences are worth evaluating? How often are we evaluating? What is the basis for the evaluation? All these are decided by us. The power is with us.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Arun Baby</name></author><category term="thoughts" /><category term="experience" /><summary type="html">It is a standard consensus that experience is the best teacher. How does just the experience can be the best teacher?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Catch up with status quo</title><link href="https://www.arunbaby.com/thoughts/status-game/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Catch up with status quo" /><published>2020-09-04T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-09-04T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>https://www.arunbaby.com/thoughts/status-game</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.arunbaby.com/thoughts/status-game/">&lt;p&gt;What if you could get rid of the idea that you always need to catch-up with your peers status wise? What changes will you make in your life? What stops you from doing that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Will you hold on to your job/relationships/activities? Do you want that shiny new object? Is that object a necessity or just a show-off to others?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Advertising has us chasing cars and clothes, working jobs we hate so we can buy shit we don’t need. We’re the middle children of history, man. No purpose or place. We have no Great War. No Great Depression. Our Great War’s a spiritual war… our Great Depression is our lives. We’ve all been raised on television to believe that one day we’d all be millionaires, and movie gods, and rock stars. But we won’t. And we’re slowly learning that fact. And we’re very, very pissed off. — fight club&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are the things we think we want are the things that we genuinely want? Or, someone had programmed you into thinking that you want it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What if you could relive yesterday? What changed would you make? What changes are you making for tomorrow?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Arun Baby</name></author><category term="thoughts" /><category term="status" /><summary type="html">What if you could get rid of the idea that you always need to catch-up with your peers status wise? What changes will you make in your life? What stops you from doing that?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Conformist</title><link href="https://www.arunbaby.com/thoughts/conformist/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Conformist" /><published>2020-09-03T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-09-03T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>https://www.arunbaby.com/thoughts/conformist</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.arunbaby.com/thoughts/conformist/">&lt;p&gt;If everything you believe is something that you are supposed to believe, what are the odds that it is really a coincidence?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How many of your opinions are you reluctant to express in front of your friends/colleagues? Why so?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the answer to the above question is ‘None’, step back and give it a thought. Odds are you are thinking in a way that you are told.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other way to get the same answer is that you independently thought about each and every possibility for each of these scenarios and end up having the exact same answer. This is a highly unlikely scenario for obvious reasons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Artists put voluntary mistakes so that they can identify when someone copies their work. So are mapmakers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What are we trading for being conformist? If every generation had only conformists, the science/technology/medicine wouldn’t have evolved this much. It’s the outlaws/renegades/uncoventionals that bring real change to the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Use your brain, start thinking about why you are thinking what you think? Are you just already too much programmed?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Arun Baby</name></author><category term="thoughts" /><category term="conformist" /><category term="learning" /><summary type="html">If everything you believe is something that you are supposed to believe, what are the odds that it is really a coincidence?</summary></entry></feed>